Guide to the photograph album S.S. Luetzow Travelogue from the Hisham Khatib Collection AD.MC.030_ref149
Akkasah: Photography Archive (NYU Abu Dhabi)
S.S. Luetzow Travelogue - Hisham Khatib Collection
1930s
Akkasah: Photography Archive (NYU Abu Dhabi)
AD.MC.030_ref149
52 Leaves - One album with string ties, containing 49 pages. Eight postcards and ship menus, forty gelatin silver photographs.
Generally good, some brittle and warped.
A photographic travelogue of a voyage taken on the S.S. Luetzow, second oriental cruise run by Norddeutscher Lloyd Bremen in April and May 1930 beginning at Venice, stopping at Istanbul, Athens, Palestine and Egypt, with handwritten notes in German. The Hisham Khatib Collection on the Holy Land and region is one of the largest collections of Middle Eastern photography still in private hands. It contains hundreds of 19th century original albumen photographic prints as well as many travel albums of the same period and early 20th century with hundreds of black and white photographs and postcards. The collection contains photography from dozens of photographers, but the albumen prints are mostly the work of the Bonfils family, Francis Frith, Francis Bedford, Matson photo Service, American Colony, Zangaki Brothers, and Frank Mason Good. Dr. Hisham Khatib has spent over 40 years amassing a vast and historically valuable collection of representations of the Near East, including the Holy Lands, including Palestine, Jordan, Turkey, Syria and Egypt. The artworks in this extraordinary collection include paintings, prints, maps, books, photographs, as well as postcards. A large part of Dr. Khatib's collection consists of rare photographic prints: he has over 3,000 images. See main collection http://dlib.nyu.edu/findingaids/html/akkasah/ad_mc_030/
Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149
Content Description
A photographic travelogue of a voyage taken on the S.S. Luetzow, second oriental cruise run by Norddeutscher Lloyd Bremen in April and May 1930 beginning at Venice, stopping at Istanbul, Athens, Palestine and Egypt, with handwritten notes in German.
Part of the Hisham Khatib Collection which contains 2,930 photographs and postcards (both individual prints and contained within albums) focussed on the Near East, including the Holy Land, Palestine, Jordan, Turkey, Syria and Egypt as well as a very small number from Europe.
Biographical / Historical
A photographic travelogue of a voyage taken on the S.S. Luetzow, second oriental cruise run by Norddeutscher Lloyd Bremen in April and May 1930. Part of the larger Hisham Khatib Collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Palestine; Jordan; Egypt; Athens, Greece; Istanbul, Turkey; Landscapes; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Boats/Ships
- Front outside cover of S.S. Luetzow Travelogue., Circa 1930; ref149_000001; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
- Front inside cover of S.S. Luetzow Travelogue., Circa 1930; ref149_000002; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  English Writing
- Breakfast menu from Second Oriental Cruise on the S.S. Luetzow, Norddeutscher Lloyd Bremen., 12 April 1930; ref149_000003; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  English Writing; Food; Boats/Ships; German Writing; Unknown Locations; Printed Materials
- Dinner menu from Second Oriental Cruise on the S.S. Luetzow, Norddeutscher Lloyd Bremen., Circa 1930; ref149_000004; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  German Writing; English Writing; Food; Boats/Ships; Printed Materials
- Postcards from Norddeutscher Lloyd Bremen, one of them picturing The Dardanelles., Circa 1930; ref149_000005; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  German Writing; Aegean Sea; Landscapes; Art; Maps; Postcards; Boats/Ships; Dardanelles Strait; Advertisements
- Dinner menu from Jerusalem Palace Hotel and Music Program from Norddeutscher Lloyd Bremen., April 1930; ref149_000006; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  German Writing; Food; Performing Arts; Boats/Ships; Hotels; Jerusalem; Palestine; Advertisements; Boats/Ships; Printed Materials
- The S.S. Luetzow in the Venice harbor and when boarding., Circa 1930; ref149_000007; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Boats/Ships; German Writing; Venice, Italy; Buildings; Ports; Palaces
- Views of Venice, Ragusa, and Perast., Circa 1930; ref149_000008; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Venice, Italy; Italy; Architecture; Seas; Buildings; Mountains/Hills; Coast; Montenegro; Palaces; Landscapes
- Views of Ragusa and Perast in the bay of Cattaro (Kotor)., Circa 1930; ref149_000009; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Italy; Seas; Mountains/Hills; Landscapes; Coast; Buildings; Montenegro
- Views of Katina, Castelnuovo, Madonna de Sealpello S. Giorgi, and Pontikonisi (Corfu)., Circa 1930; ref149_000010; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Seas; Mountains/Hills; Landscapes; Coast; Italy; Greece; German Writing; Buildings; Greece
- Corfu Old Fort and signal station., Circa 1930; ref149_000011; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Forts/Castles; Buildings; Greece; Seas; Coast
- Views of Corfu and the Sultan Ahmed Mosque., Circa 1930; ref149_000012; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Landscapes; Seas; Greece; Buildings; Constantinople; Blue Mosque/Sultan Ahmed Mosque; Mosques; Architecture; Religious Sites; Istanbul, Turkey
- The Hagia Sophia and Süleymaniye Mosque., Circa 1930; ref149_000013; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Hagia Sophia; Suleymaniye Mosque; Istanbul, Turkey; Architecture; Mosques; Religious Sites; Buildings; Landscapes
- Views of the Golden Horn and Galata., Circa 1930; ref149_000014; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Galata, Istanbul, Turkey; The Golden Horn/Haliç; Architecture; German Writing; Landscapes
- The S.S. Luetzow at Galata Pier, Istanbul, and docked in Skutari (Üsküdar)., Circa 1930; ref149_000015; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Galata, Istanbul, Turkey; Istanbul, Turkey; Boats/Ships; Uskudar, Istanbul, Turkey; Architecture; Landscapes
- Views of Sultan Ahmed Mosque., Circa 1930; ref149_000016; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Blue Mosque/Sultan Ahmed Mosque; Architecture; Istanbul, Turkey; Outdoors; Mosques; Buildings; Religious Sites
- Barracks and graveyard in Scutari (Üsküdar)., Circa 1930; ref149_000017; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Cemeteries; Outdoors; Officials; Buildings; Uskudar, Istanbul, Turkey; Landscapes
- Views of Anadoluhisarı, Rumelihisarı, the Bosphorus and beginning of the Black Sea., Circa 1930; ref149_000018; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Bosphorus; Black Sea; Forts/Castles; Architecture; Landscapes; Istanbul, Turkey; Buildings
- Views of the Bosphorus., Circa 1930; ref149_000019; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Bosphorus; German Writing; Landscapes; Seas; Buildings; Coast
- Views of the Bosphorus, Gallipoli and the Helles Memorial., Circa 1930; ref149_000020; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Black Sea; Bosphorus; Dardanelles Strait; Cemeteries; Istanbul, Turkey; Landscapes
- The Dardanelles, Athens Hotel, and the road from Piraeus to Athens., Circa 1930; ref149_000021; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Dardanelles Strait; Streets/Roads; Hotels; Athens, Greece; Buildings; Outdoors; Landscapes
- Temple of Athena Nike and Panathenaic Stadium in Athens., Circa 1930; ref149_000022; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Athens, Greece; Temples; Monuments/Memorials; Stadiums; Outdoors; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Crowds; Religious Sites
- Theseion (Hephaestus), Erechtheion, and the Acropolis from Mt. Lycabettus., Circa 1930; ref149_000023; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Acropolis of Athens; Temples; Crowds; Buildings; Architecture; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Athens, Greece; German Writing; Landscapes
- A group of people at the Acropolis and views of the Parthenon., Circa 1930; ref149_000024; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Crowds; Men; Women; Outdoors; Acropolis of Athens; Athens, Greece; Temples; Architecture; Buildings; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Group Portraits; Hats; Binoculars; Religious Sites; Landscapes
- A group of people ascending the Acropolis and the Cemetery of Kerameikos., Circa 1930; ref149_000025; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Acropolis of Athens; Buildings; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Architecture; Crowds; Cemeteries; Outdoors; German Writing
- The Temple of Zeus and a group of people at the Acropolis., Circa 1930; ref149_000026; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Group Portraits; Men; Women; Outdoors; Temples; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Architecture; Hats; Religious Sites
- Museum, chapel and a group of people at Eleusis., Circa 1930; ref149_000027; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Greece; Churches; Crowds; Men; Women; Outdoors; Museums; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Architecture; Religious Sites; German Writing; Group Portraits; Binoculars
- Views of Propylaea., Circa 1930; ref149_000028; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Athens, Greece; Acropolis of Athens; Buildings; Architecture; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Outdoors; German Writing
- The Erechtheion, and a group of people at Erechtheion., Circa 1930; ref149_000029; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Acropolis of Athens; Temples; Buildings; Architecture; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Outdoors; Men; Women; Athens, Greece; Group Portraits; Hats
- Views of Propylaea and Santorini Island., Circa 1930; ref149_000030; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Greece; Athens, Greece; Acropolis of Athens; Outdoors; Aegean Sea; Coast; German Writing; Men; Buildings; Landscapes
- Haifa, the Mount of Olives and Al-Aqsa Mosque., Circa 1930; ref149_000031; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Haifa; Palestine; Temple Mount/al-Ḥaram al-Šarīf; Mount of Olives/Jabal al-Zaytun, Jerusalem; Jerusalem; Al-Aqsa Mosque/al-Masjid al-ʾAqṣā; Outdoors; Mosques; Landscapes
- Temple Mount and view to the Mount of Olives., Circa 1930; ref149_000032; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Jerusalem; Temple Mount/al-Ḥaram al-Šarīf; Mount of Olives/Jabal al-Zaytun, Jerusalem; Outdoors; Religious Sites; Architecture; German Writing; Palestine; Men; Women; Landscapes
- Streets in Jerusalem, the Holy Sepulchre, Jaffa Gate and the Western Wall., Circa 1930; ref149_000033; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Jerusalem; Jaffa Gate, Jerusalem; Streets/Roads; Outdoors; Church of the Holy Sepulchre; Western Wall; Religious Sites; Architecture; Buildings; Palestine; Praying; Churches; Shops
- Views of Jerusalem, the Augusta Victoria Hospital and British Military Cemetery., Circa 1930; ref149_000034; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Jerusalem; Mount of Olives/Jabal al-Zaytun, Jerusalem; Cemeteries; Religious Sites; Palestine; Dome of the Rock/Qubbat al-Sakhrah; Regional/National Dress; Hospitals; Landscapes; Men; Temple Mount/al-Ḥaram al-Šarīf; Military/Soldiers
- Jerusalem City Wall, Hinnom Valley, Kidron Valley and Garden of the Lutheran Church of the Redeemer., Circa 1930; ref149_000035; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Gehenna/Valley of Hinnom; Jerusalem; Churches; Religious Sites; Kidron Valley; Gardens; Palestine; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Landscapes; Buildings
- Rachel's Tomb and views of Bethlehem., Circa 1930; ref149_000036; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Tombs/Mausoleums; Bethlehem; Religious Sites; Camels; Streets/Roads; Bilal bin Rabah Mosque/Rachel's Tomb; Palestine; Men; Cars/Trucks; Regional/National Dress; Animals; Churches; Fez/Tarboush; Buildings; Landscapes; Hats
- Streets in Bethlehem., Circa 1930; ref149_000037; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Bethlehem; Outdoors; Streets/Roads; Palestine; Men; Regional/National Dress; Buildings; Mosques; Buildings
- Baptism Site at the Jordan River, St. George Monastery in Wadi Qelt and houses in Nazareth., Circa 1930; ref149_000038; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Nazareth; Monasteries/Convents; Monastery of St. George of Choziba; Buildings; Jordan River; Religious Sites; Palestine; Women; Rivers; Landscapes
- Funerary Complex of Sultan al-Ashraf Barsbay and Khanqah al-Nasir Faraj ibn Barquq, views of the Sphinx and Pyramids of Giza and a group riding camels., Circa 1930; ref149_000039; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Cairo, Egypt; The Great Sphinx of Giza; Pyramids; Mosques; Khanqah-Mausoleum of Sultan Barsbay; Camels; Religious Sites; Architecture; Monuments/Memorials; Women; Men; Turbans; Hats; Regional/National Dress; Camels; Donkeys; Tombs/Mausoleums; Giza, Egypt; Landscapes
- Sphinx of Giza and the Pyramid of Cheops (the Great Pyramid)., Circa 1930; ref149_000040; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Monuments/Memorials; Giza, Egypt; The Great Sphinx of Giza; Pyramids; Outdoors; Camels; Crowds; Men; Women
- A group riding camels at the Pyramids and the Cairo Citadel., Circa 1930; ref149_000041; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Cairo, Egypt; Citadel, Cairo, Egypt; Monuments/Memorials; Pyramids; Outdoors; Camels; Crowds; Men; Women; Hats; Regional/National Dress; Advertisements; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Giza, Egypt; Forts/Castles; Mosque of Muhammad Ali Pasha
- Al-Rifa'i and Sultan Hassan mosques, the Sphinx of Memphis and a water wheel., Circa 1930; ref149_000042; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Cairo, Egypt; Mosques; Memphis, Egypt; Monuments/Memorials; Religious Sites; Architecture; Buildings; Water; Outdoors; Mosque-Madrassa of Sultan Hassan; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Irrigation; Cattle/Cows; Animals; Cars/Trucks; Transportation
- Views of Saqqara, Memphis and Giza., Circa 1930; ref149_000043; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Saqqara, Egypt; Memphis, Egypt; Pyramids; Giza, Egypt; Monuments/Memorials; Camels; Outdoors; Architecture; Animals; Palm Trees; Landscapes
- Buildings in Heliopolis including Our Lady of Heliopolis Co-Cathedral and the Baron Empain Palace., Circa 1930; ref149_000044; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; German Writing; Heliopolis, Cairo, Egypt; Cairo, Egypt; Buildings; Palaces; Churches; Religious Sites; Architecture
- Excerpt from the Norddeutscher Lloyd Bremen's journal showing a hand-colored ship illustration and a postcard of a relief depicting Gethsemane., Circa 1930; ref149_000045; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  German Writing; Postcards; Boats/Ships; Gethsemane, Jerusalem; Religious Imagery; Religious Sites; Advertisements; Palestine; Hand-colored Photographs/Hand-tinting
- The Sphinx, the Mosque-Madrassa of Sultan Hassan and Al-Rifa'i., Circa 1930; ref149_000046; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; The Great Sphinx of Giza; Giza, Egypt; Mosques; Architecture; Monuments/Memorials; Religious Sites; Cairo, Egypt; Mosque-Madrassa of Sultan Hassan; Pyramids
- Blank page., Circa 1930; ref149_000047; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
- A building with a crow-stepped gable., Circa 1930; ref149_000048; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Europe; Churches; Religious Sites; Buildings; Outdoors; Europe
- A building with turrets and spires., Circa 1930; ref149_000049; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Europe; Churches; Religious Sites; Buildings; Outdoors; Europe; Architecture
- Blank page., Circa 1930; ref149_000050; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
- Inside back cover of S.S. Luetzow Travelogue., Circa 1930; ref149_000051; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)
- Outside back cover of S.S. Luetzow Travelogue., Circa 1930; ref149_000052; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital Copy Only 030_ref149)